# 你看 酸酸甜甜的那個贛南臍橙嘗鮮款的
Look! The sweet and sour ones, I mean, the early bird orders of the Southern Jiangxi navel oranges,
(filmed in 10th November, 2020)
# 現在已經全部打包好啦
have all been packed now.
(filmed in 10th November, 2020)
# 過兩天就可以採那個又大又黃的
We can start picking the big and golden ones in a couple of days.
# 這裡都是借用兄弟家的院子打包的
These packs are now placed in the backyard borrowed from my buddy.
# 幸好他這裡有院子 要不然就不好搞啦
So lucky that he has a backyard here. Otherwise it would be big headache.
# 你看 他們在裝車
Look! They’re now loading onto the trucks.
# 兩輛車還有一輛車還沒來 稍微等一下
Here are now two trucks. One is coming. Gotta wait for a while.
# 你看 現在他們車來啦 來了三輛大卡車哦
Look! All trucks are here now, three big trucks.
# 都是順風的專車
They are chartered from the courier company.
# 這些人都是請到我們村裡的人
These people are hired from our own village.
# 有些四五十歲的 五六十歲的也有
Some are in their forties, and some are in their fifties.
# 七十歲的好像爺爺 在車廂裡面就做沒那麼辛苦的
Those in their seventies, like the grandpas, they're doing some easier jobs in the trucks.
# 老的嫩的都來幫忙
Everybody is coming to help, old or young.
# 要不是他們的話 估計貨都發不出來
Without them, I don’t think we can dispatch any orders.
# 他們挺 一叫他們就到 挺配合的
They’re rather… They come immediately upon my request. They’re rather cooperative.
# 等下我去看一下兄弟家的臍橙 看黃的怎麼樣啦
I’m gonna have a look at my buddy’s navel oranges and see how ripe they are now.
# 如果黃了之後就更好吃啦
They would taste even better when they become golden yellow.
# 哎呀 看他們裝一下貨
Aya! Let me watch them loading.
# 剛才我也 剛才我也搬了一下貨 搞得腰酸背痛的
I’ve also, I’ve also joined them for a while. It hurts my back.
# 感覺我都老啦 是啊 他們
I seem to be getting old. Yea, they’re,
# 好多都是六十歳左右的
many of them are around sixty.
# 他們都
They’re all,
# 挺厲害的感覺
they all seem very tough and strong.
# 你看 這些都快黃啦
Look! These will become ripe very soon.
# 有些都幾乎都黃啦
Some are actually already ripe.
# 但是有些 你看 這些果
But some are... Look! These oranges,
# 好多這些斑點 因為這些 很少 很少打藥
there are a lot of these kind of dots. Cuz they seldom, seldom put pesticides.
# 所以造成很多斑點
That’s why there are so many dots.
# 其實沒事的 口感都是一樣的
But in fact it doesn’t matter. The taste is the same.
# 你看 這些 這些都黃了哦
Look! These, these are ripe now.
# 這邊 這邊還有
Here, more here
# 你看 這些 沒洗的果就是這樣 有點這個斑點
Look! These are, there are always some dots if the oranges are not washed.
# 要是如果洗了的話 就是會把那個表皮會擦傷
But if they're washed, it’s like, the surface may be damaged.
# 擦傷之後就要放保鮮劑
And if the surface is damaged, you need to put preservatives.
# 如果不放保鮮yx這個果就很快壞掉
Without preservatives, the oranges may become rotten very quickly.
# 所以我們賣的這個 這個果啊
So the, the oranges, that we sell here,
# 就是直接剪下來就直接發貨啦
are cut right away from the trees and dispatched right away.
# 所以說就
So I mean,
# 沒洗 所以看上去就有點髒
we don’t wash them. So they look a bit dirty.
# 其實這個沒事的哦
But in fact it doesn’t matter, you know.
# 洗洗就可以吃的
Just wash them and then it can be eaten.
# 如果 如果洗了果就 又放保鮮劑就更 更不好吃啦
If, if we wash them here, and put the preservatives, it would only make it taste bad.
# 擰一個吃一下
Let me twist off one and have a try.
# 這個口感差不多都上來啦
The taste seems to be already there.
# 還是黃的哦 如果轉紅色的話
It’s still golden yellow, you know. If they turn red,
# 如果轉紅色的話 最少 最少要到這個月月底才會轉紅色
if they turn red… They won’t turn red until at least, at least the end of this month.
# 轉紅色的話就要全部要摘掉
Once they turn red, they all need to be picked.
# 不摘掉的話就會壞掉啦
Otherwise they would be rotten.
# 嗯
Um!
# 可以哦 橙子味很足
No bad! It’s very flavourful.
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 你看 正常的果就是這樣的 摘下來的果就是這樣子的哦
Look! That’s how the oranges should be, how they should be when they’re picked from the trees, you know.
# 這個有點小疤 或者這個有點
There are some small scars, or here are some,
# 那個水滴 哦 掉下來 沒事
some droplets. Oh! It drops. No worries.
# 你看 市場上買那個很漂亮的果啊
Look! The very pretty ones that you buy from the markets,
# 它就要先洗一下 然後再放點保鮮劑
they’re always washed, and then stored with preservatives.
# 看上去就很漂亮
So they look really pretty.
# 但是我們的果園直接發出來的果就是這樣子的哦
But those dispatched right away from our orchard look like this one.
# 其實這樣還好吧
In fact it's pretty fine, isn’t it?
# 原生態的味道
That’s the taste of the nature.
# 更漂亮
They're even prettier.
# 你看 這個
Look! This one!
# 我吃一個哦 看看味道怎麼樣
Let me have one, and see how it taste.
# 你看 這個汁 皮上這個汁都
Look! The juice, the juice on the peel is already,
# 噴出來
bursting out.
# 像我們這個果就是等下說 如果今天下訂單的話
Our oranges here are, like, if the order is placed today,
# 明兩天我們就 搞下來就直接發貨啦
we're gonna pick and dispatch them right away in one or two days.
# 啊啊 這個果肉可以吧
Ah ah! The pulp is not bad, isn’t it?
# 嗯
Um!
# 很不錯 好香啊
Really not bad! It smells so good!
# 啊 兄弟家的味道
Ah! It’s the at-my-buddy’s-place taste.
# 要不好嘗一點啊
You want some?
# 可以 很甜啦 現在
Not bad. It’s really sweet now.
# 口感都上來啦
The taste is already there.
# 這幾天出太陽
It’s sunny these few days.
# 天氣都比較好
The weather is rather good.
# 一下子就黃啦
So they become ripe very quickly.
# 你看 這些還 還有點青
Look! This is still, still a bit green.
# 這個青不要緊
But it doesn’t matter.
# 這些可以吃啦 這個就有點太青啦 這個
It can be eaten now. But this one is a bit too green, this one.
# 怪不得兄弟家的果 好多那個疤
My buddy uses this one instead of pesticides. No wonder,
# 用這個來除蟲
that there are so many scars on his fruits.
# 你看 這裡也有這個很漂亮的哦
Look! Here’s also a very pretty one, you know.
# 就是有些很漂亮 有些不怎麼好看
It’s like, some are really pretty, while some are not quite.
# 都行
But both are as good.
# 剛才吃了兩個
I’ve just eaten two.
# 味道很不錯咯 現在
They taste really not bad, really not bad now.
# 再過幾天的話更好
It would be even better after a couple of days.
# 你看 這些光綫好的黃的更快喲
Look! When they have enough sunshine, they become ripe even sooner.
# 這些都黃透啦
These are completely ripe now.
# 你看 這是
Look! These are,
# 果園裡面還有這個拿藤包
there are also chocolate vine fruits in this orchard.
# 哇 那麼大
Wa! So big!
# 這個更大 這個
This is even bigger, this one.
# 這一個
This one
# 第二天
The next day
# 現在在挑摘哦 把那個黃的全部挑下來
They’re now choosing the right ones to pick. They pick all the golden yellow ones.
# 青的就讓它撓在樹上 讓它黃了再摘
They green ones are left in the tree. They’ll be picked when they become ripe.
# 叫了十幾二十個人
We’ve hired ten or twenty people.
# 這些果就漂亮吧 都是黃的
These oranges are really pretty, aren’t they? They’re all golden yellow.
# 挑一個最小的來
Let me choose the smallest one.
# 嗯 好甜
Um! Sweet!
# 不信你吃一下
Try it and you’ll know that I’m not lying.
# 你都不吃酸的
I know. You don’t like sour oranges.
# 全是果肉
It’s only pulp here.
# 這個果就已經完全熟啦
These oranges are all completely ripe now.
# 如果放幾天的話 更甜
They would be even sweeter if they’re stored for a few more days.